玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
ln the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的时间 空间和物质
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...of time, space, and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence...
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
潜伏在太阳系的暗处
Lurking in the shadows of the solar system...
那些世界非常具有化学活性 千奇百怪
are worlds so chemically active and misshapen...
它们近乎怪诞
that they border on the bizarre.
我觉得最令人震惊的
That l think the most shocking thing...
是太阳系居然如此千姿百态
was howvery different the solar system is.
这些是卫星
These are the moons...
围绕着太阳系里的行星
surrounding the planets of the solar system...
曾经是要么身份不明
moons that were once either unknown...
要么就是事后想当然
or considered afterthoughts...
这些卫星现在处于天文探索的前沿
are now on the cutting edge of astronomical exploration.
出人意料的是
What was surprising...
它们的模样根本就不像我们的月球
that they all didn't look like our moon.
所谓的太阳系里次要成员
The so-called minor members of the solar systems...
影响并不次要
are not of minor interest.
这些地外卫星会给我们带来哪些惊喜呢？
What surprises await us on these alien moons?
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第五集 地外卫星
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 05of19 Alien.Moons
我们的太阳系对科幻作家来说一直就是块沃土
Our solar system has always been fertile ground...for science fiction writers...
但是随着望远镜技术的飞速发展
but with exponential advances in telescopic technology...
无人探测器的亲密接触
and close encounters by unmanned probes...
新的卫星芭蕾的帷幕已经拉开
the curtain has now been lifted on a new ballet of moons.
其中多数往一个方向运转
Most of which are going one way around...
其中有些会往另一个方向运转
some of which are going the otherway around...
都以不同的速度相互经过
all at different rates, passing one another...
里面的经过外面的
the inner ones passing the outer ones.
近半个世纪里
For nearly half a century...
认为太阳系里只有32颗卫星
it was believed the solar system was home to only 32 moons.
它们大小不等 从木星的卫星
They ranged in size from Jupiter's moon...
木卫三其比水星还大
Ganymede, larger than the planet Mercury...
到小行星状的个头
to small asteroid-shaped ones...
比如火星的卫星火卫一 火卫二
like the Martian moons Phobos and Deimos.
数目迅速扩大
That number has exploded.
仅2007年一年科学家宣布
ln 2007 alone, scientists announced...
发现了20颗新卫星围绕着木星
the discovery of 20 new moons around Jupiter...
一颗围绕着土星
one around Saturn...
三颗围绕着海王星
and three around Neptune.
天文望远镜能够看到它们的原因
What happened is astronomical telescopes...
就在于所谓的CCD相机
had available to them what are called CCD cameras.
这些是数码相机
These are digital cameras...
现在几乎是人手一个
that almost everybody has nowadays.
难在天文学家准确掌握
lt's difficult to hold astronomers...
太阳系里的卫星数目
to an exact number of moons in the solar system.
随着相机变得更加敏感及望远镜的更加强大
As cameras become more sensitive and telescopes more powerful...
越来越多的卫星露出了本来面目
more moons reveal themselves.
卫星分为截然不同的两类
Moons are classified in two distinct ways.
那些像我们的月球那样在它们的行星赤道的上方的
Those like our moon travel in nearly circular orbits...
近圆轨道上运行的叫做规则卫星
above their planet's equators and are called regular moons.
在我们的月球形成于一次撞击的时候
While our moon formed from an impact...
其它所有的规则卫星则在其母星周围的
all other regular moons coalesced...from the gaseous stew...
气态云里凝聚起来
surrounding their parent planets...
这个过程称为吸积
a process known as accretion.
规则卫星的典型例子
The classic example of regular moons...
将是木星的伽利略发现的卫星
would be the Galilean moons of Jupiter...
木卫一 木卫二
lo, Europa...
木卫三和木卫四
Ganymede, and Callisto.
其材料也是形成木星的
The material that is going to form Jupiter, too...
但是稍微延展了一些
but extended a little bit...
那些材料聚集成了卫星
that material accumulates into the moons.
卫星沿着拉长的轨道
Moons that follow elongated orbits...
高度倾斜在他们的行星赤道上
highly tilted to their planet's equators...
被称为不规则卫星
are called irregular moons.
其中多数运行在逆行轨道上
Most of these move in retrograde orbits...
顺时针运转 而它们的行星则逆时针旋转
clockwise if their planet rotates counterclockwise.
土卫九… 新发现的木星的卫星
Phoebe, the newly discovered moon orbiting Saturn...
就是一个理想的例子
is a perfect example.
她开始自己的太空生活
She began her celestial life...
是作为一个围绕太阳的逍遥自在的游客
as an independent traveler orbiting the sun...
之后才被较大的土星所捕获
before being captured by the more massive Saturn.
不管规则还是不规则
Whether regular or irregular...
卫星都必须置身于其母行星的引力范围内
moons must fall within the gravitational reach...of their parent planet.
这些轨道的界限被称为希尔球
The limit of these orbits is known as the Hill sphere.
这个现象的命名来自乔治·威廉·希尔
This phenomenon is named after George William Hill...
19世纪中叶的美国天文学家
an American astronomer from the mid-1800s.
当然希尔球就是行星周围的这个区域
So a Hill sphere is this region around the planet...
随着行星移动
that moves along with the planet...
其中行星的引力
inside of which the gravity of the planet...
压倒了太阳的引力
overwhelms the gravity of the sun.
火星的卫星… 火卫二 火卫一
The moons of Mars, Deimos and Phobos...
在希尔球里的运行完全不一样
operate very differently within the Hill sphere.
如果行星运转得快于
lfthe planet is rotating faster...
卫星的运转 比如火卫二
than the moon it orbits, like Deimos...
二者之间的潮汐力
the tidal forces between the two...
实际上会将火卫二推出去越来越远
actually shove Deimos out further and further.
而另一方面 火卫一
Phobos, on the other hand...
运转快于火星的运转
is rotating faster than Mars rotates.
这些小卫星是由
These small moons were discovered...
美国天文学家亚萨·希尔在1877年发现的
byAmerican astronomer Asaph Hall in 1877.
他的命名来自希腊的害怕之神福波斯[火卫一]
He named Phobos after the Greek god offear...
和恐怖之神迪摩斯[火卫二]
and Deimos for the god of terror.
汤姆·达克斯伯里隶属水手9号任务
Tom Duxburywas part of the Mariner 9 mission...
在1971年11月首次对这两颗土豆状卫星拍照
that first photographed the two potato-shaped moons...in November of 1971.
那是一个深夜
This was late at night...
一个寒冷 多雨 黑暗 阴沉的日子
on a cold, rainy, dark, dreary day...
我望着这个
and l looked at this...
我把图像转向侧面
and l turned the picture sideways.
看上去像个可怕的骷髅
lt looked like a skull, and it was such an eerie thing.
火卫一简直是是死亡旋转[death spiral]
Phobos is in a death spiral.
其轨道距离火星表面只有3700英里
lt orbits just 3,700 miles from the Martian surface...
比我们太阳系里的任何卫星都更接近其母行星
closer to its host planet...than any moon in our solar system.
如果我们的月球距离地球
lf our own moon were as close to the Earth...
如火卫一距离火星一样近的话 其看上去就要大上20倍
as Phobos is to Mars, it would look 20 times larger.
其轨道周期就几个小时
lts orbital period would be in hours...
不像现在以天计 而是以时计算
not days like it is now, but hours.
在满月时将撑满天空
And at full moon, it would fill the sky.
每天的潮汐 要知道潮涨潮落
The daily tides, you know, would rise and fall...
数十英尺甚至数百英尺高
tens offeet if not hundreds offeet...
因此地球的卫星
and so the Earth's moon...
最终会在那样的情况下撞上地球
would eventually crash into the Earth...in such a situation.
形成火卫一的窘境的过程
Phobos' predicament is caused by a process...
称为长期加速
known as secular acceleration.
由于火卫一的速度大于火星的旋转速度
As Phobos races faster than Mars rotates...
火星表面形成了潮汐隆起
a tidal bump is raised on the Martian surface.
在这个过程中每一圈火星都将火卫一猛拉近自己的表面
ln the process, Mars yanks Phobos closer to its surface...with each orbit.
火星与火卫一之间的搏斗
The struggle between Mars and Phobos...
就像是简单的绳球游戏的动力学
is similar to the dynamics of a simple game of tetherball.
把球看作是卫星 柱子看作是行星
lmagine the ball as the moon, the pole as the planet...
球柱之间的绳子
and the rope between the pole and the ball...
就像是行星拉扯的引力
as the planet's gravitational pull.
我们看到的是引力
What we see is that the gravity...
以这样一种方式拉住卫星
would pull the moon in such a way...
使其加速
that it speeds up.
它走得越来越快 往这个方向运转
lt goes faster and faster, and it works its way...
直至最终撞上柱子
until it eventually hits the pole.
那就是火卫一的情况
That's exactlywhat's happening to Phobos.
火卫一为围绕着火星运转快于火星的旋转
Phobos is going around Mars faster than Mars rotates.
那个潮汐互动
That tidal interaction...
正将火卫一拉得越来越近
is pulling Phobos in closer and closer...
其运转也越来越快
and speeding it up in its orbit.
在约5000万年里
ln about 50 million years...
我们预计火卫一将被拉得很近
we expect Phobos to be pulled in so closely...
将会撞上火星 火星的一颗卫星将不复存在
it will impact Mars and disappear as a moon of Mars.
而另一方面火卫二是逐步往外的卫星
On the other hand, Deimos, the further-out moon...
其运转要慢于火星的旋转
is going slower than Mars rotates.
因此它以相反的方向解开绳子
And so it's unwinding the string in the opposite way...
我们所见到的是火卫二
and what we see is Deimos...
正越来越远离火星
is going further and further away from Mars.
最终
And eventually...
火卫二将在太阳的引力下拉离火星
Deimos will be pulled away from Mars...by the gravity of the sun.
因此随着时间的推移火星将失去卫星
So, over time, Mars will become moonless.
因为火卫一快于火星的旋转
Because Phobos outpaces the rotation of Mars...
它升起在西方而降落在东方
it appears to rise in the west and set in the east.
不同于行星在其下面转动很快
lnstead of the planet turning quickly under it...
比如我们的月球和大多数其它卫星那样
like our moon and most other moons...
在东方升 西方降
and thus having it rise in the east...and set in the west...
它跑在了行星的旋转的前面了
it races ahead of the rotation of the planet.
所以它会在西方地平线上升起
And so it comes up on the western horizon...
一路奔跑降落在东方的地平线
and races ahead and sets on the eastern horizon.
还有5000万年
lt will be another 50 millions years...
火卫一才会彻底消失
before Phobos completely disappears.
在那之前它有可能证明对最终殖民火星是有用的
Before then, it may prove useful...for the eventual colonization of Mars.
科幻作家阿瑟·C·克拉克
Science fiction writer Arthur C. Clarke...
在其著作《火星之沙》中提出了这个想法
speculated on this idea...in his book "The Sands of Mars."
尽管没有殖民火卫一本身的真正的理由
Although there is no real reason to colonize Phobos itself...
但是它靠近火星使其成为了天然的中途小站
its close proximity to Mars makes it a natural waystation.
从引力的角度出发
From a gravity standpoint...
到达没有重力的火卫一要更多地容易于
it's much easier to go to Phobos...which has no gravity...
对抗火星的引力
than it is to fight the gravity of Mars...
降落在其表面
to get down to this surface.
从伽利略到斯坦利·库布里克
From Galileo to Stanley Kubrick...
太阳系外围的大行星
the giant planets of the outer solar system...
挑逗我们想象力的是其庞大
have tantalized our imagination with their enormity.
然而事实上探索它们无异于自杀
But in reality, exploring them is tantamount to suicide.
来自木星厚重的大气层的巨大压力
The overwhelming pressure...from Jupiter's massive atmosphere...
将使其几乎无法动弹
would make it almost impossible to function.
然而这些庞然大物的卫星
But the moons of these behemoths...
可以提供较有希望的平台
may provide a more promising platform...
用于探索甚至下一步的殖民
for exploration and even future colonization.
这些木星引力的俘虏究竟是
Are these prisoners of Jupiter's gravity...
维持原始生命机会甚少的不友善世界？
hostile worlds with little chance...of sustaining organic life?
还是能为将来的几代星际探索者提供一个安全港呢？
Or might they provide a safe haven...for future generations of planetary explorers?
直到最近我们对这些气体
Until recently, very little was known...
冰雪巨人卫星了解少得可怜
about the moons of the gas and ice giants.
其中大多数隐匿在其母行星的炫光之中
Most of them remained hidden in the glare...of their parent planets.
如今现代望远镜和无人空间探索器
Today, modern telescopes and unmanned space exploration...
揭示的区域居住有大群的卫星
reveal a realm populated by a host of moons...
从行星状的球星世界
from planet-like spherical worlds...
到只有30英里直径的奇怪天体
to misshapen ones barely 30 miles across.
木星… 太阳系里最大的行星是卫星的吸引者
Jupiter, the largest planet in the solar system...is a moon magnet.
约45亿年前
Nearly 4.5 billion years ago...
它诞生于自身塌缩的巨大的气体云里
it began as a massive gas cloud collapsing in on itself.
这个过程 称为吸积
This process, known as accretion...
形成了木星系的开端
formed the beginnings of the Jovian system.
虽然几乎所有的气体和旋转物质
While nearly all the gas and spinning material...
都进去形成了木星本身
went into forming Jupiter itself...
但是还是有很小比例堆积在木星轨道上的小漩涡里
a very small percentage clumped in small eddies...within Jupiter's orbit.
这些微型附属物
These miniature accretions...
凝固成了木星的规则卫星
solidified into Jupiter's regular moons...
木卫一 木卫二 木卫三和木卫四
lo, Europa, Ganymede, and Callisto.
随着木星的凝结 其巨大的引力
As Jupiter coalesced, its massive gravity...
从太阳系诞生早期就开始施加给了这些小不点群
began adding to its menagerie little remaining bits...from the birth of the early solar system.
巨型行星早期形成于气体丰富的环境中
The giant planets formed early in a gas-rich environment...
当时有大量的流浪者
when there was lots of little flotsam and jetsam...
飘荡在太阳系里直至被捕捉进轨道
around the solar system still to be captured into orbit.
木星的卫星数量范围从60颗到200多颗
The number of Jupiter's moons ranges from 60 to over 200...
取决于统计的人
depending on who's counting.
明确的是
What's clear is...
要是你站在木星的大气层边缘
if you could stand at the edge...of Jupiter's gaseous atmosphere...
仰望天空
and look to the heavens...
你就会看到卫星之类的天体壮丽的舞蹈
you'd see a magnificent dance of lunar objects.
看上去酷毙了 能够看到卫星
lt would look pretty cool to be able to see the moons.
偶尔你可以看到木卫一经过
Every so often, you'd see lo come by.
每两次看到木卫一经过
Every second time lo comes by...
你都能够同时看到木卫二
you'd see Europa at the same time.
而木卫一每四次经过
And every four times lo comes by...
你就可以看到木卫三
you'd see Ganymede.
这个木星剧组的一个成员
One member of this Jovian cast...
饱受木星巨大质量的煎熬
is so battered by Jupiter's great mass...
正在一点点从里到外炸开
that it is literally bursting from the inside out.
2007年的2月新地平线飞船
ln February of 2007, the New Horizons spacecraft...
最终驶向冥王星
eventually bound for Pluto...
相机对准了木卫一
focused its cameras on lo.
差不多月球的个头
About the size of Earth's moon...
其轨道距离木星表面26.3万英里
it orbits 263,000 miles from Jupiter's surface.
木卫一区别于其它木星卫星的
What sets lo apart from the other Jovian moons...
是其壮观的火山喷发
is its spectacularvolcanism.
新地平线的相机
New Horizons' cameras...
捕捉到了分布在木卫一表面的滚滚熔岩的详细图像
captured detailed photos of glowing lava...scattered across lo's surface.
巨大的200英里高的尘缕升起在熔岩卫星的表面
A huge 200-mile-high dust plume rose above the surface...of the molten moon.
瞧 木卫一和其它木星的规则卫星一样
lo, like all Jupiter's regular moons...
是以罗马神话里的爱神邱比特的情人来命名的
is named after a lover of the god Jupiter...from Roman mythology.
它是伽利略在1610年发现的
lt was discovered by Galileo in 1610...
首次拍照是先驱者一号在1974年
first photographed by Pioneer l in 1974...
再次拍照是航行者一号在1979年
and again byVoyager l in 1979.
其脉动的活力困惑了科学家几十个年头
lts pulsating activity has puzzled...and intrigued scientists for decades.
喷出木卫一的物质约每秒钟一吨
Leaving lo is about a ton per second of material...
日夜不停
every second of every day.
这是台非凡的机器
lt's a phenomenal machine.
我欲前往木卫一
l would like to go to lo...
即使它非常险恶
even though it would be very dangerous...
高温 充满硫磺
and hot and sulfurous.
木卫一太小了 自其形成以来不足以保持一个熔核
lo is too small to have maintained a molten core...since its formation.
另一个神秘的过程
Another mysterious process...
必定对其持续的高温负责
must be responsible for its heating.
木卫一的整个内部有可能是熔化的
lo's entire interior may be molten...
因为它围绕木星运转所以受到极大的挤压
because it's squeezed so much as it's orbiting around Jupiter.
这个过程被称为潮汐加热
This process is known as tidal heating.
木星巨大的引力
The massive gravity of Jupiter...
引起了木卫一内核的摩擦
is causing friction at the inner core of lo.
极像雕刻家揉冷泥团
Much like a sculptor kneads a cold lump of clay...
木星在不停地打造自己的作品
Jupiter is endlessly creating its own masterpiece.
如果卫星得到那么一点潮汐加热
lf a moon gets a little bit of tidal heating...
就会变得柔韧
it becomes malleable.
就会像泥巴那样延展
lt can be stretched out like clay...
在母行星的引力下变形
and deformed by the gravity of the parent planet.
卫星的表面是寒冷的
The surface of the moon is cold.
它像泥巴那样很快就被扯开 开裂
lt breaks like pulling clay apart quickly. lt'll break.
然而在其内部是热的
But the interior, where it's warm...
会慢慢流动延展
can literally flow and stretch...
被其母行星的引力搓揉
and be kneaded by the gravity of the parent planet.
多数规则卫星的轨道是圆形轨道
Most regular moons have circular orbits.
为了产生潮汐加热
To produce tidal heating...
卫星必须在一个较为椭圆的轨道上
a moon must be in a more oblong orbit...
其距离母行星的距离
where the distance from the host planet...
在自己的运行中固定改变
changes radically during a single revolution.
产生这些偏心轨道的唯一途径
The only way to produce these eccentric orbits...
就是有另一颗卫星的引力在骚扰它
is if another moon's gravity disrupts it.
卫星一旦处于椭圆轨道
When a moon is in an eccentric orbit...
非圆轨道
a non-round orbit...
就会接近以及远离其母行星
it gets closer and farther from its parent planet.
一旦这样它就受到挤压
When it does, it gets squeezed.
它接近时会受到拉扯
lt gets pulled apart when it's closer.
木卫一处在轨道共振中
lo is in orbital resonance...
是其伙伴卫星木卫二 木卫三引起的
with its companion moons Europa and Ganymede.
虽然木星和木卫一在努力找到
While Jupiter and lo struggle to find...
一种同步关系
a synchronistic relationship...
木卫二和木卫三
Europa and Ganymede...
却在逆向拽拉着木卫一
are yanking lo in opposite directions.
木星在后面拽拉
Jupiteryanks back...
木卫一在这个过程中受到拉伸和挤压
and lo gets stretched and squeezed in the process.
对木卫一的潮汐加热
The tidal heating on lo...
是形成其异常的火山的原因所在
which is responsible for its prodigious volcanoes...
还有第二个作用
has a secondary side effect.
它创造了太阳系里最大的静止有形物体
lt creates the largest stationary visible object...in the solar system...
相当于木星体积500倍的巨大的气体云
a massive gas cloud 500 times the size of Jupiter.
1990年迈克尔·门迪洛教授
ln 1990, Professor Michael Mendillo...
以及他波斯顿大学的小组
and his team from Boston University...
发现了一个跨度极大的气体云
discovered a large gas cloud spanning the huge distance...
从木星的一面到另一面
from one side of Jupiter to the other.
他们首次拍摄到了整个星云
They were the first to photograph...
发现了它的起源
the entire nebula, discover its origins...
以及保持其不断增长的机制
and the mechanism that keeps it growing.
木卫一不大
Now, lo is small...
所以它不可能有太多的大气
so it doesn't have much of an atmosphere.
然而这些火山
But these volcanoes...
源源不断地提供着可能构成大气层的物质
are continually providing material...that could be an atmosphere.
然而你可能会问
But you might ask...
那为什么它会没有巨大的大气层
"Well, why doesn't it have tremendous atmosphere...
如果所有的火山亿万年来一直都在喷发的话？
if all the volcanoes have been going on for eons?"
这是因为物质逃逸了
Well, it's because the material escapes.
关键的气体是钠
The key gas is sodium.
虽然它只占木卫一喷射物的5%
Even though it only makes up five percent...of lo's ejected materials...
但是在地球上用望远镜还是很容易观察到
it is easily detectable by telescopes on Earth.
钠发出橙色的光芒
Sodium emits an orange glow.
事实上钠被普遍用于世界上许多城市的路灯上
ln fact, sodium is commonly used to illuminate streetlights...in many cities across the world.
钠和其它气体分子
The sodium and the other gas molecules...
遭到了太阳光和强大的木星磁场里的电子的轰击
are pelted by light from the sun...and electrons in Jupiter's powerful magnetic field.
电子和质子遭到撞击
Electrons and protons are knocked off...
某些粒子被电离了
some of these particles and ionized.
在电离状态中
Now in plasma form...
这些离子被木星强大的磁气圈裹挟而行
these ions are taken on a ride...by Jupiter"s powerful magnetosphere.
其速度明显增加
lts speed increases dramatically...
因为它被磁场牢牢抓住了
because it's been picked up by the magnetic field.
它们就像是骑上了宇宙旋转木马
lt's like they're taking a ride on a cosmic carousel.
这里的磁力线很强
The magnetic field lines are the poles here.
于是时不时的
And then every now and then...
钠原子会逮住这个电子一起前行
a sodium atom gets picked up along with this electron.
现在我加入了木星的等离子合唱队
And now, l'm in the Jupiter plasma chorus...
和所有先前所捕获的离子和电子一起
with all the other ions and electrons...that have been captured previously...
离子和电子重新组合起来
and the ions and the electrons recombine.
不带电 已不再受到磁场的限制
The neutral is not confined by the magnetic field...
它以很高的速度离开
and it goes off at a much higher speed...
足以摆脱木星
and that's enough to escape from Jupiter.
它们形成了太阳系里永恒的最大的有形气体云
And they form the largest visible cloud of gas...that's permanently in the solar system.
如果我们用肉眼可以看到这星云的话
lf we could see the nebula with the naked eye...
在夜空中会有12个月亮那么大
it would be the size of12 moons in the night sky.
它非常大所以为了能观察它
lt is so enormous that to view it...
门迪洛和他的小组打造了自己特殊的望远镜
Mendillo and his team created their own specialized telescope.
啊 事实证明为了获得大视场
Well, as it turns out, to get a big field ofview...
你所需要的一切就是小透镜
all you need is a small lens...
比如双筒望远镜就可以为你提供一个大视场
like a pair of binoculars gives you a big field ofview.
即使是在1991年望远镜可能看似普通
Even in 1991, the telescope may have seemed ordinary...
但是其相机确实非常先进的
but its camera was highly sophisticated...
当代创新的数码相机
and, at the time, revolutionary...the digital camera.
一旦你获得了大量的图像
Once you've got a picture that's in numbers...
你就可以对其进行各种研究了
you can do all kinds of things with it.
门迪洛和他的小组知道了
Mendillo and his team knew...
钠存在于星云中
that sodium existed in the nebula.
钠同时也存在于地球的大气层里
Sodium also exists in the Earth's atmosphere.
他们能够比对木星和地球大气层的数码相片
They were able to compare digital photographs...of both Jupiter and Earth's atmospheres...
提出那星云的影像
and bring forth an image of the nebula.
要做到是很困难的
Well, that was very difficult to do...
如果你只有两幅照片和几页纸的话
if youjust had two photographs and pieces of paper.
然而现在我们有了数码相机
But now that we have these digital cameras...
我们就彻底改变了处理图像的手段了
we've revolutionized the way that we can process images.
尽管木卫一是个相当迷人的
Though lo would be a fascinating...
科学和美学的目标
scientific and aesthetic destination...
但是其不友好的环境有可能给予了否定
its hostile environment probably precludes that.
甚至无人探测器都很难登陆
Even landing an unmanned probe would be difficult...
木卫一摇晃不停的裂隙之中
among lo's convulsing fissures.
然而还有一颗卫星围绕着木星
But there's another moon orbiting Jupiter...
它可能不仅能支持人类的探索
which may not only support human exploration...
而且还有可能支持其自己的地外生命的形成
but possibly support its own alien life forms.
木卫二是我们太阳系里最迷人
Europa is one of the most fascinating...
最神秘莫测的天体之一
and enigmatic objects in our solar system...
确实不像太阳系的其他地方
really unlike anyplace else in the solar system...
就此而言其一点都不像地球
and for that matter, unlike anything on Earth.
其表面特征就是
The surface features are such...
表面存在着裂缝
that there are cracks in the surface...
斑驳混乱的地形
there's mottled terrain, there's chaotic terrain...
某些地方看上去好像有冰山
and it looks like icebergs in some areas.
我们知道木卫二是一颗地外卫星
We know Europa is an alien moon.
它同样会成为地外生命的形成之地吗？
Could it be home to alien life forms as well?
木卫二的轨道距离木星表面有40万英里
Europa orbits 400,000 miles from Jupiter's surface...
约是木卫一距离的两倍
about double the distance of lo.
和它颤抖不停的堂兄一样
And like its convulsive cousin...
它也是引力潮汐造就的
it too is molded by gravitational tides.
木星具有最大的影响力
Jupiter has the greatest effect.
它的个头就像一个坚持不懈的情人
lts mass, like a persistent lover...
将不情愿的卫星拉向自己的表面
pulls the reluctant moon toward its surface.
木卫二以自己的引力加以对抗
Europa resists with its own gravity...
它们形成了一种共存关系
and they form a kind of symbiosis...
高踞气体巨星上方数十万英里
hundreds of thousands of miles above the gas giant.
然而不光是木星在拽拉着木卫二
But it's not just Jupiter tugging at Europa.
小木卫一和大堂兄木卫三
Little lo and larger cousin Ganymede...
也从另外的方向拉着木卫二
pull at Europa from different directions.
就是这同样的轨道共振
lt's the same orbital resonance...
对木卫一产生了戏剧般的影响
that has such a dramatic effect on lo.
不管怎样 其结果远不同于木卫二
However, the results are far different on Europa.
木卫二的表面十分寒冷
Europa's surface is cold...
某些地方是负的550华氏度
minus 550 degrees fahrenheit in some places...
然而还是在加热
yet there is heating.
木卫二表面冒出的东西
And what rises to the surface of Europa...
也是让这颗卫星如此让人兴奋的东西 - 水
is also what makes the moon so exciting: water.
这个水实际上是一种流动的冰从地下海洋中冒出 透出地表
This water, actually a kind of glacial ice...is rising from an underground ocean...and oozing out onto the surface...
像磨冰机做溜冰场那样重新铺就
repaving it as a Zamboni does an ice rink.
木卫二的海洋被认为位置不深
Europa's ocean is thought to be shallow...
就在其地表下面10到15英里处
only about10 or15 miles below the surface.
水是地球上生命的摇篮
Waterwas the cradle of life on Earth.
在木卫二或其它卫星上会同样成真吗？
Could the same be true on Europa or other moons?
冰冷的卫星海洋会成为宇宙间生命最普遍的栖息地
lcy satellite oceans could be the most common habitat...that exists in the universe.
地球可能相对较为罕见
Earths might be relatively rare...
然而冰冷的卫星或许比比皆是
but icy satellites are probably plentiful.
2007年2月新地平线飞船
ln February of 2007, the New Horizons spacecraft...
前往冥王星和太阳系的外围并设法足够近地飞经木卫二
on its way to Pluto...and the outer reaches of the solar system...managed to fly close enough to Europa...
发回了一些惊人的图像
to send back some startling pictures.
只有在木卫二日出日落背后看到的
Seen only as the sun is rising or setting behind Europa...
是惊人的地质图案
are enormous geological patterns...
已经被戏称为麦田怪圈
that have been dubbed crop circles.
它们非常大
They are very large.
如果你想 告诉你
lfyou were to, you know...
试图横穿一个麦圈
try to drive across one of the circles...
你就会逐步进入 一路往下
you would very, you know, gently go in and travel down...
来到的地方要比你出发的地表低几百英尺
to a location that's a few hundred feet lower...than the surface you came up from...
然后再慢慢升高
and then rise back up.
类似于地球上的麦田怪圈
The resemblance of Europa's crop circles...
地球上乡间各地的神秘之物
to the mysterious ones that dot the countryside here on Earth...
关键要考虑它们的规模
ends when you consider their size.
每一个的直径有2000到3000英里
Each one is 2,000 to 3,000 miles in diameter.
它们很浅 清一色成为了撞击火山
They're too shallow and uniform to be impact craters.
小行星和彗星具有不同的大小和形状
Asteroids and comets come in different sizes and shapes.
木卫二的麦田怪圈地质现象惊人地类似
Europa's crop circles are remarkably similar geologically.
尽管未经证实
Although nothing has been proven...
似乎木星巨大的质量
it seems the great mass of Jupiter...
可能再次会成为罪魁祸首
may once again be the culprit.
据推测
The speculation is...
覆盖木卫二表面的冰盖
that the icy covering surrounding Europa...
并没有拴在卫星核上
is not tethered to the core of the moon.
相反它像球形冰盖那样飘浮在地下海洋上
Rather, it's floating above the subsurface ocean...like a spherical iceberg.
极地地区可能就是在木星塑造下
The polar region may be somehow shaped by Jupiter...
然后经过了无数年
and then over hundreds of thousands of years...
慢慢拉向了赤道
slowly tugged toward the equator.
这构成了小环状洼地排成一线
This forms a line of small circle depressions...
从极地落向赤道
dropping from the polar region toward the equator.
如果木卫二的冰类似于地球冰盖的构造那么其大部分会在水面下
lf Europa's ice crust...has similar structure to icebergs on Earth...most of it would be under the ocean's surface.
这对未来的探索具有重大的影响
This has huge implications forfuture exploration.
这意味着必定有8到9倍的冰量
lt means there has to be something like eight...
在其下面
or nine times that amount of ice underneath them to allow...
认为是大规模的地质构造
that kind of a large-scale topography to exist.
冰盖理论平息了这种说法
The iceberg theory lays to rest the belief...
即木卫二的地下海洋可以很容易通过薄壳来获得
that Europa's subsurface ocean can be easily tapped...through a thin crust.
雷达测绘和紫外线数据的结果
Radar mapping and ultraviolet data...
对木卫二着陆器登陆前是尤为重要的
will prove to be even more important...
到时这有利于登陆车在木卫二地表着陆
before a Europa lander...can make its way down to the surface.
未来的探测器将得搜寻
Future explorers will have to search out hot spots...
这个神秘的海洋存在的几处会涌出地表的热点
in places where this mysterious ocean...has welled up through the surface...
并从那里设法找到潜入的途径
and from there try to find a way to dip into it.
那些探测器会转而选择
Those explorers may choose instead...
将作业基地建在木卫三
to set up a base of operations on Ganymede...
这个木星最大的卫星上
Jupiter's largest moon.
由于木卫一可能会被用作火星探测的中转小站
As Phobos might serve Martian exploration...as a waystation...
木卫三就有可能在木星系里承担同样的作用
Ganymede might do the same for the Jovian system.
木卫三个头大于水星且重力比任何木星的卫星都接近地球
Larger than the planet Mercury...its gravity is closer to that of Earth's...than any of Jupiter's moons.
虽然都是在其势力范围内但是由于木卫一和木卫二
And though it's in orbital residence...with both lo and Europa...
距离木星尚不够远到能够较少地
it's far enough away from Jupiter to be less affected...
受到这颗气体巨星无情潮汐的影响
by the gas giant's relentless tides.
而对于木卫三 可以这么说
And at Ganymede, you could, say...
在一些合适的大火山坑里
park in some nice, big crater...
建造你的圆顶保护区
and build your domed, protected region...
来防御木星系里的带电粒子
protected from the charged particles...in the Jovian system...
打造一个相当安全的基地来研究木卫三本身及它的磁场
and make a pretty safe place to study...not just Ganymede itself and its magnetic field...
它的内部结构 它的地质情况
and its interior and its geology...
而且还有整个木星系
but the Jupiter system as a whole.
木卫三在整个太阳系里是唯一的一颗卫星
Ganymede is the only moon in the solar system...
有着自己的磁场
with its own magnetic field.
为了具有这个特征
To have this distinction...
木卫三就必须有足够的质量
Ganymede must have sufficient mass...
以及炙热的内核
and a hot inner core.
它的质量是显而易见的
lts mass is obvious...
但是其热的来源可有点搞不大清楚
but where the heat is coming from...is a bit of a mystery.
木卫三受到木卫一和木卫二两者的潮汐力的共同影响
Ganymede is affected by both lo and Europa's tidal forces.
但是对其轨道的测量表明
But the measurements on its orbit indicate...
它的运转足以避免其堂兄弟所遭受到的
that it's round enough to avoid the squashing and stretching...
来自木星的挤压和拉伸
that its smaller cousins endure from Jupiter.
认为是木卫三在过去或许发生了某种事情
The thought is...maybe something happened in Ganymede's past...
从而稍稍改变了自己的轨道
to change its orbit slightly...
或许它的偏心在有段时间里有点失控
and maybe its eccentricity got kind of haywire...for a little while...
木卫三内部产生了大量的热量引起了其内核变热
and generated a lot of heat within Ganymede...and caused the core to be hot.
我们还确实不清楚
We don't really know.
我们所知道的是
What we do know...
新地平线最近飞越了木星系
is that New Horizons' recent flyby...of the Jovian system...
给我们带来了我们所期待的木星地外卫星那迷人的匆匆一瞥
gave us a tantalizing glimpse of the wonders that await us...on Jupiter's alien moons.
科学家期盼着有那么一天
Scientists look forward to the day...
能够登陆这些卫星中的一颗
a lander touches down on one of these moons...
开始揭开这些神秘世界的秘密
and starts to uncover the secrets...of these mysterious worlds.
另一颗冰封的卫星围绕着气体巨星土星运转
Another icy moon orbits the gas giant Saturn.
它实在太小了以至无法守住自己的大气层
lt's too small to hold onto its own atmosphere...
然而这并不阻止它慢慢消耗其母行星的大气层
but that doesn't stop it...from sapping the atmosphere of its parent planet.
土卫二尽管很小
Enceladus, even though quite small...
但却是以希腊神话里的巨人部落来命名的
is named after a tribe of giants in Greek mythology.
和木卫一和木卫二一样
Like lo and Europa...
土卫二具有一个偏心轨道
Enceladus has an eccentric orbit...
围绕着其母行星土星运转
around its parent planet Saturn.
土星的潮汐力
The tidal forces of Saturn...
挤压和搓揉着这颗小卫星
squeeze and knead this tiny moon...
使其内核产生了热量
and create heat at its core.
然而不同于木卫一
But unlike lo...
它没有回涌出熔化的物质
it doesn't regurgitate molten material...
它合并进了巨大的气体云里
it coalesces into a massive gas cloud.
水并未在其表面涌出
Water doesn't well up to the surface...
如冰冷的木卫二那样
as it does on icy Europa.
不 土卫二实际上是将冰水的烟柱
No, Enceladus actually spits plumes of icy water...
喷入土星的大气层中
into the atmosphere of Saturn.
所以我们不能将此称为火山
So we don't call it a volcano.
它更多的像是间歇泉
lt's more like a geyser.
水蒸汽于是进入围绕这颗小卫星的轨道
The watervapor is then in orbit...around the little tiny moon...
或者是因为它靠近土星
or because it's near Saturn...
土星的引力会将它拉进行星
Saturn's gravity can pull it into the planet.
受他们对木卫一环面研究的启示
lnterested by theirwork on the torus of lo...
迈克尔·门迪洛和他的波士顿大学的小组
Michael Mendillo and his team at Boston University...
着手考虑土星大气层对土卫二的影响
began to consider Enceladus' effect...on Saturn's atmosphere.
事实证明水对于离子与电子重组
And it turns out that water is a wonderful catalyst...
是极好的催化剂
to have the ions and electrons recombine.
在卡西尼探测器之前科学家依赖通过计算机模型
Before Cassini, scientists relied on computer models...
来测定土星周围的大气环境
to determine atmospheric conditions surrounding Saturn.
他们指出土星应该有一个非常强大的电离层
They indicated that Saturn should have...a very robust ionosphere.
令人惊讶的是卡西尼号的数据表明
Surprisingly, Cassini's data indicated...
土星的电离层只有计算机模型所预测的一成
that Saturn's ionosphere was only10 percent...of what computer models had predicted.
似乎土卫二所喷出的冰水
lt seems that the icy water ejected from Enceladus...
中和了土星电离层里的带电粒子
is neutralizing the charged particles...in Saturn's ionosphere.
开始升空
Commence lift off.
科学家已经很偶然地认识到了
Scientists had learned quite by accident...
水可以影响到地球的大气层
the effect water can have on Earth's atmosphere.
1973年美国航天局发射了太空实验室
ln 1973, when Nasa launched its Skylab workshop...
发射了最新的巨大的土星5型火箭
it launched its last gigantic Saturn V rocket...
月球火箭
the moon rocket.
它从来没有过一次发射
And it had never had a launch...
让航天器在电离层那样的高度保持发动机的燃烧
that allowed the space vehicle...to keep its engine burning as high as the ionosphere.
这个巨大的发动机
Well, this gigantic engine...
每秒钟泻出一吨水蒸汽
dumped a ton per second of water vapor...
这是巨大的火箭发动机喷进电离层的
which comes out of a giant rocket motor...into the ionosphere.
而那天的电离层几乎消失了
And the ionosphere nearly vanished on that day.
它在地球的电离层里炸出了一个大洞
lt blew a gaping hole in Earth's ionosphere...
大气层的顶层
the top layer of the atmosphere...
这个洞让太阳的电离辐射修补了24个小时
a hole that took the sun's ionizing radiation...24 hours to repair.
然而在土星上
However, on Saturn...
土卫二每分钟6吨水连续不断地喷入它的大气层里
where Enceladus continuously dumps...six tons of water per minute into its atmosphere...
其长期影响是相当可观的
the long-term effects have been significant.
不用担心土卫二会剥离其母行星的电离层
There's no worry that Enceladus will strip away...its parent planet's ionosphere completely...
但是这颗小小的卫星只有300英里的直径
but this tiny moon, only 300 miles in diameter...
已经引起了科学界以及土星本身的关注
has gotten the attention of the scientific community...and Saturn itself.
在我们准备探测火卫一和木卫二
While we prepare probes to Phobos and Europa...
研究来自土卫二和木卫一的资料的时候
and study data from Enceladus and lo...
一个全新的卫星系列已经逐个走进视野
an entirely new set of moons...has literally just come into the picture.
上世纪90年代前 多数天文学家认为
Before the 1990s, most astronomers agreed...
太阳系里只有34个卫星
that there were only 34 moons in the solar system.
其中的多数是我们月球这样的规则卫星
Most of those were regular moons like our own...
球星的身躯围绕着母行星
spherical bodies that orbit their host planet...
以同样的方向旋转
in the same direction it rotates.
然而这些卫星中的少数
But a handful of these satellites...
是所谓的不规则卫星
were what's known as irregular moons.
这些怪异的卫星拖着拉长的轨道
These freakish moons follow elongated orbits.
它们的轨道通常是倾斜的
Their orbits are often tilted...
它们的旋转方向与其母行星刚好相反
and they rotate in the opposite direction...of their host planets.
它们看上去就像是在飞行的土豆碎片或奇形怪状的大块
They look like flying potatoes or splinters or misshapen lumps.
它们以前很难被发现那是因为它们很小 同时它们通常也很暗淡
They've been hard to find before now...because they're very small...and they're also usually very dark.
数码照相技术的出现
The advent of digital photography...
光敏光学的使用
and the use of light-sensitive optics...
在十年里改变了卫星的地形地貌
changed the lunar terrain within a decade.
布雷特·格莱德曼博士
Dr. Brett Gladman...
来自英属哥伦比亚大学
from the University of British Columbia...
在1997年发现了他的第一颗不规则卫星
discovered his first irregular moon in 1997...
是在帕洛马天文台
at the Palomar Observatory.
此后格莱德曼博士揭示了
Since then, Dr. Gladman has brought to light...
17个太阳系里以前隐藏的对象
17 previously hidden objects in the solar system.
这样你发现了外太阳系里的对象
So you detect objects in the outer solar system...
通过观察它们的移动
by observing them move...
相对于在背景中静止的星星与星系
relevant to the background stars and galaxies...which are stationary.
如果你拍摄夜空照片后再等上一个小时
So if you take a picture of the sky...and you wait an hour...
你再拍一次夜空
and you take another picture of the sky...
银河系里的没有一颗恒星会移动
none of the stars in the galaxy will have moved...
但是在外太阳系里的遥远的对象
but distant objects in the outer solar system...
会在两幅照片中移动可观的量
will displace by a visible amount...between the two pictures.
因此通过比对两幅照片
And so by comparing the two pictures...
你可以看到这里有一个移动的目标
you can see, as we have here, a moving target.
这个对象可以是彗星也可以是小行星
The object could be a comet or an asteroid...
或者它以倒退的方式围绕着一颗行星
or, if it orbits a planet in a retrograde fashion...
那就是一颗新的不规则卫星
a new irregular moon.
规则卫星与其不规则同行之间的另一个重要区别
Another important distinction between regular moons...and their irregular counterparts...
在于不规则卫星是捕获的
irregular moons are captured.
也就是它们的形成与它们的母行星无关
That is, they formed...independently of their host planet...
最有可能是形成我们太阳系的原始碎片的部分
and most likely were part of the debris...that originally formed our solar system.
土卫九… 围绕土星的最大的不规则卫星
Phoebe, the largest irregular moon orbiting Saturn...
是个典型的例子
is a classic example.
土卫九围绕土星非常极端
Phoebe orbits Saturn very far out.
它具有一个非常椭圆 非常倾斜的轨道
lt has a very elliptical and very inclined orbit.
它的运行是倒退方向
lt orbits in a retrograde direction.
航行者的图像表明
Voyager images suggested...
这个东西的模样就像是个小行星
that this thing looks like it could be an asteroid...
所以人们也许会认为它是颗被俘获的小行星
and so people thought maybe it is a captured asteroid.
现在我们通过卡西尼号了解到它是个富含水的天体
Nowwe knowfrom Cassini it's a very waterized-rich body.
那几乎就排除出了小行星带
That pretty much rules out the asteroid belt.
意见是土卫九极有可能是来自柯伊伯带
The thinking is that Phoebe could very well have come...from the Kuiper Belt...
来自太阳系的外围
way out in the outer reaches of the solar system.
柯伊伯带被认为是太阳系形成后残留的碎片
The Kuiper Belt is thought to be the debris left over...after the solar system formed.
它在冥王星轨道以外围绕着太阳运转
lt revolves around the sun beyond the orbit of Pluto.
然而另一个理论提出了全然不同的意见
However, another theory...suggests something altogether different.
更多地倾向于土卫九形成于
lt's much more likely that Phoebe formed...
独立围绕太阳的轨道上
in an independent orbit around the sun...
然后被捕获进入了围绕土星的轨道
and then was captured into orbit around Saturn...
而其它在土星附近形成的多数对象要么是与土星共生的
whereas most of the other objects...that formed near Saturn's distance...were either accreted by Saturn...
要么就是从太阳系里赶出来的
or ejected from the solar system.
土卫九有可能是由土星诞生时漂浮
Phoebe would then be made of the planetary debris...
在其周围的行星碎片形成的
that was floating around Saturn at the time of its birth.
有可能其不同物质的成分
And possibly it;s made up of different material...
要多于围绕木星的不规则卫星
than some of the irregular moons orbiting Jupiter.
如果是这样的话
lf this is the case...
天文地质学家就有可能辨别和比较
astrogeologists may be able to discern and compare...
这两颗气体巨星诞生时的不同成分
the different ingredients...that birthed these two gas giants.
现存三个主要的理论
Three main theories currently exist...
关于土卫九以及其它不规则卫星是如何
as to how Phoebe and its other irregular counterparts...
丧失自己的独立性的
lost their independence.
有两个提出不规则卫星是在太阳系形成时被捕获的
Two suggest the irregulars were captured...as the solar system was still forming...
当时行星还是个气体与碎片共同组成的星团
and the planets were still an accreting blob...of gas and debris.
气体拖曳理论最简单
The gas-drag theory is the most straightforward.
稠密的气体围绕着正在增大的行星旋转
Thick gases were swirling around the accreting planet...
当彗星 小行星经过这气团时 或许两者粉碎性地合并
when a comet, asteroid...or a shattered combination of both...passed through the gaseous mixture.
我们知道气体行星
We know that the giant planets...
在围绕着各个行星巨大的吸积盘里
built their regular satellite systems...
构建了自己的规则卫星系统
in a large accretion disc around each of the planets...
有点像一个迷你太阳系
sort of like a mini little solar system...
形成于各个行星的周围
forming around each planet.
在那个吸积盘里的气体和尘埃
And the gas and dust that was in that disc...
同样也会呆在外围
can also serve in its outer regions...
作为冲突的根源
as a source offriction...
在那里经过的独立形成的小行星体
where passing planetesimals formed independently...
会放慢脚步而被捕获入轨
are slowed down a little bit and captured into orbit.
第二个理论实际上是第一个的变化版
The second theory is really a variation on the first.
它有时被称为吸入理论
lt's sometimes called the pull-down theory.
这里并不是物体简单经过共生气团时被抓获的
Here, instead of an object being caught...by simply passing through the accreting gases...
而是不自觉地被不断增强的引力
it is unsuspectingly pulled...into the forming planet's orbit...
吸入正在形成的行星轨道的
by its growing gravitational pull.
捕获的气体拖曳和吸入说
The gas-drag and the pull-down theories of capture...
都能够很好适用于木星和土星
work well for both Jupiter and Saturn...
因为它们的混合体十分巨大
because their mixture of ingredients...
足以放慢这些经过的物体的脚步
was massive enough to slow down these passing objects.
然而对于海王星和天王星这样的冰冻巨星说的通吗？
But what about the icy giants Neptune and Uranus?
由于极端地寒冷所以它们的形成非常的缓慢
Because of the extreme cold, they formed much more slowly...
难以相信它们的冰积混合物里
and it's difficult to believe...
含有足够的质量来捕捉经过的太阳系的碎片
that their icy accretion mixture contained enough mass...to snare a passing piece of the solar system.
但是这两个冰冻巨星都有着自己的不规则卫星
Yet both icy giants have their own irregular moons...
因此有了第三个理论:三体互动说
hence, a third theory: three-body interaction.
我们发现 物体中有许多实际上是不止一个物体
We discover that many of the objects...
它们实际上是两个物体
are actually more than one object.
通常是因为它们两个几乎个头差不多且与另一个有着二元关系
They're usually two objects...often that because they're both more or less the same size...as the other in a binary relationship.
不是作为一个大的物体
lnstead of being a big object...
带着一个小的物体围绕着它这样运转
with a small object going in an orbit around it like this...
而是几乎两个差不多大小的物体
it's two more or less similar-sized objects...
围绕着一个共同的轨道运转
going around a common orbit.
两者之间称为重心
Between the two of them is called the barycenter.
二元共存
A binary pair exists...
此时两个同样大小的物体
when two objects of the same size...
与重心贴得足够近
are tight enough to the barycenter...
以防止第三个较大的物体将它们拆散
to prevent a third larger object from splitting them apart.
然而一旦两者之间的一个
But when one of the binary pair...
稍稍比另一个大一点时
is significantly larger than the other...
较大的第三者就有较大的机会来拆散它们
the more massive third object...has a greater chance of separating them.
较小的那个就会趋向大很多的轨道
The smaller one will tend to have the much bigger orbit...
向外甩去
swing out further.
这就造成了较小的物体
This brings the smaller object...
足以靠近行星而被捕获
close enough to the planet to be captured...
此时它的伙伴就被甩进一个独立的轨道
while its partner is slung out into an independent orbit.
有个怪异的卫星似乎难以归类
One bizarre moon seems to defy classification.
海卫一以逆行的方式围绕着海王星
Triton orbits Neptune in a retrograde fashion...
逆着海王星的旋转方向
counter to Neptune's rotation.
这就使得它成为了一颗不规则卫星
That would make it an irregular moon...
除了它是球状的
except that it's spherical...
以及轨道靠近赤道
and orbits close to the equator...
是一个几近完美的圆周
with an almost perfectly round circumference...
典型的规则卫星的式样外
a classical description of a regular moon.
它也喷发出神秘的冰烟柱
lt also spews out mysterious icy plumes...
一些迹象表明这里曾经有过
with some indication that it once was...
或者依然有可能有火山活动
or possibly still is volcanically active.
在旅行者2号闯入外太阳系之前
Before Voyager 2 ventured into the outer solar system...
海王星的卫星海卫一曾被假设是
Neptune's moon Triton was assumed to be...
地质生命已经死亡的岩石球
a geologically dead ball of rock...
与我们的月球一般大小
about the size of our own moon.
旅行者发回的照片
When Voyager beamed back photographs...
揭示了这个世界具有山脉
revealing a world with mountains...
断层线 裂隙
fault lines, and fissures...
象征着构造运动
indicative of tectonic movement...
以及令人惊艳的稠密的大气层
as well as a surprisingly thick atmosphere...
科学家们为之震惊
scientists were amazed.
一般存在于许多温度较高
Geologic forces usually associated...
较大的行星上的地质力量
with much warmer and larger planets...
有可能存在于比我们月球稍小的冰冻卫星上
might be occurring on a frozen moon...slightly smaller than our own.
1989年旅行者发现没有活火山
Voyager detected no active volcanoes in 1989.
然而像土星的卫星土卫二
However, like Saturn's moon Enceladus...
间歇泉会定期在星球表面喷发
geysers periodically erupted from the planet's surface.
海卫一真正令人吃惊的
What's really stunning about Triton...
不只是具有一些地质过程的发生
is not just that it has...some unique geological processes occurring...
而是事实上是发生在海卫一这样一颗不规则卫星上
but the fact that they're happening...even though Triton is an irregular moon.
太阳系里多数大卫星
Most large moons in the solar system...
都是规则卫星
are regular satellites...
由于海卫一的极其重大的例外
with the very important exception of Triton...
海王星最大的卫星
Neptune's largest moon...
走错了路
which orbits the wrong way.
所以海卫一被认为一直是颗俘获的物体
So Triton is thought to have been a captured object.
像规则卫星那样活动的俘获卫星
A captured moon that acts like a regular one.
海卫一大小的物体是如何做到
How did an object the size of Triton...
速度降慢到
slow down enough...
既不穿过海王星的大气层
not to either pass through Neptune's atmosphere...
又不直接撞上冰冷的行星的呢？
or collide directly into the icy planet?
没有确切的把握
There's no sure bet...
但是有些理论带来了较好的机会
but some theories carry better odds.
很像轮盘赌的赌徒
Much like gamblers at the roulette wheel...
海卫一和海王星在博弈
Triton and Neptune played the odds...
全凭运气
and trusted to luck.
投注 看运气啦
Place your bets. Get lucky now.
在轮盘赌上有几种投注的手段
ln roulette, there are several ways to bet.
每一个都带来不同的机会
Each one carries different odds.
和多数凭运气的游戏一样
And like most games of chance...
机会越小回报就越高
the longer the odds, the greater the payoff.
20黑 双20黑
20 black, 20 black even.
至少有三种可能的途径
There are at least three possible ways...
海卫一不会被海王星所捕获
Triton could've been captured by Neptune.
所有这三个假设都是物理上的可能
All three hypotheses are physically possible...
然而第一个 气体拖曳的想法
but the first one, the idea of gas drag...
是最有可能的
is the least likely...
只是因为在海王星具有气体和尘埃盘的时期里
simply because the period of time...which Neptune had a disc of gas and dust...
是不可能捕获到海卫一这样的对象的
which could've captured a proto Triton object...
而在非常短暂的时段里
it was a very short period of time...
所以说机会之窗是很小的
and so the window of opportunity was very small.
所以这就像是在轮盘赌台面上投注在绿0上
So that's like betting on the green zero...on the roulette table.
最有可能的是海卫一的原型
More likely is the possibility that the proto Triton...
曾经在太阳系历史上某个时刻
sometime in the solar system history...
撞上了一组规则的中等个头的冰卫星
crashed into a set of a regular...middle-sized icy satellites...
也就是碰撞给我们带来了海卫一
and it was the collision which gave us Triton.
那就像是在轮盘赌台面上第一排
And that's like betting on the first third...
第三个数字上赌一把
of the numbers on the roulette table...
所以你就像是有三中一的机会
so you have, like, a one-in-three chance...of that taking place.
你最好的办法是投注在偶数上
Your best bet is to bet on the even numbers.
这样你就有二分之一的机会
There you have a one-in-two chance...of things happening.
而刚好捕捉到海卫一的最佳办法
And the best bet for the capture of Triton right now...
就是这个成双捕获的假设
is this binary capture hypothesis because there...
我们知道柯伊伯带大概存在着数千个物体
we know there are probably thousands of objects...that had existed in the Kuiper Belt...
具有适当的个头
that would have the right size...
会与另一个更大的物体结伴
and be partnered with another even larger object...
海王星就有可能捕获到其中的一个
and Neptune could capture one of them.
没人清楚海王星俘获海卫一时
No one knows for sure which number paid...
早期太阳系里的具体数目
in the early days of the solar system...when Neptune captured Triton.
不管怎样一旦海卫一以不规则的模样
However, once Triton began orbiting Neptune...
开始围绕海王星运转后
in an irregularfashion...
它就开始清除挡道的所有东西了
it started obliterating anything that got in its way.
海王星没有一个非常规则的卫星系统
Neptune doesn't have a very regular system of satellites.
被认为海卫一的俘获
lt's thought that the capture of Triton...
破坏了说不定会像其它大行星
disrupted what would've otherwise been...
那样所具有的很规则的系统
a nice regular system...like the other large planets have.
就好象海卫一愤怒于失去了自己的自由
lt's as if Triton was angry at losing its freedom...
泄愤于海王星的其它倒霉的卫星身上
and took it out on Neptune's other hapless moons.
然而这颗任性的卫星究竟是从何而来的呢？
But where did this headstrong moon come from?
旅行者2号发回的数据表明
Data from Voyager 2 indicates...
海卫一的密度几乎与冥王星不相上下
that Triton's density nearly matches Pluto's.
这表明没有其它规则卫星可以与其攀亲的
This suggests a kinship...that no other regular moon can claim.
怀疑冥王星和海卫一
lt's suspected that Pluto and Triton...
双双都是诞生于柯伊伯带的物体
are both objects that originated in the Kuiper Belt.
外太阳系
The outer solar system...
由这些大物体组成
consisted of these large objects...
基本上在到处游荡
going every which way, essentially.
其中的一些形成了大行星本身
And some of them formed giant planets themselves...
其中的一些被抛得更遥远
and some of them were tossed out further...
到了如今的柯伊伯带
where they sit today in the Kuiper Belt.
碰撞 吸积乃至捕获都大为减少了
Collisions, accretions...and even captures have diminished...
那曾经是行星建材的主要大通道
what was once a major thoroughfare...of planetary building materials.
在太阳系历史的早期
Early in solar system history...
柯伊伯带有非常多的大物体
the Kuiper Belt had far more larger objects...
可能聚集了大量的物质其质量相当于50个地球
that may have once had a cumulative mass...of 50 Earths...
而目前柯伊伯带的质量比一个地球小很多
whereas the current Kuiper Belt mass...is much less than one Earth.
柯伊伯带里残留的东西
What's left of the Kuiper Belt...
和太阳系本身一样古老
is as old as the solar system itself.
构成成双物体的物质
The material that makes up the binary objects...
碰撞的碎片 甚至一些地外卫星
shards of collisions, and even some alien moons...
40亿年以来没什么变化
hasn't changed in overfour billion years.
令人惊异的是
lt's amazing how really different...
外太阳系里的各个卫星真是千姿百态
all the moons of the outer solar system are.
在我对天文学开始感兴趣时
When l first got interested in astronomy...
当时还是1960年代的一个孩子
as a kid in the 1960s...
我们还没有发现任何一颗卫星
we hadn't seen any of these moons.
它们是你望远镜里的小不点
They were little dots in your telescope...
所以我们没有概念
and so we had no idea...
它们会有怎样的千差万别
how radically different they could be.
但是我认为最震惊的事情是
But l think the most shocking thing...
太阳系里居然有这么多的种类
was how, you know, much variety there is...in the solar system.
我认为那震撼了我以及所有经历了那个时期的人
l think that blew me and everybody else away...who lived through that period.
在我们从我们太阳系很冷的外围
As we travel back home...
一路旅行回家
from the frigid outskirts of our solar system...
对宇宙的浩瀚 行星的壮丽充满了敬畏的同时
awed by the vastness of the universe...and the majesty of the planets...
也有必要关注一下躲在暗处的小小世界
it's worth it to pause and take notice...of the small worlds in the shadows.
那些地外卫星曾经一再被认为是
Those alien moons that were once considered after thoughts...
掌握着秘密 就等待着人类的好奇心去揭示了
hold mysteries just waiting...for human curiosity to solve.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing